Finding Aid for Santiago Artiaga papers, 1914-1957
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Santiago Artiaga papers 1914-1957
Artiaga, Santiago, 1878-1962.
0.3 linear feet.
85696 Aa 2
City engineer in the Philippines; correspondence, biographical materials, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was primarily the gift of Santiago Artiaga (donor no. 3511 ) and came to the library in 1948 and 1959.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Santiago Artiaga was a 1904 graduate of the College of Engineering of the University of Michigan. With his degree in civil engineering, he returned to the Philippines. In 1920, he became Manila's City Engineer, serving until 1936. In addition, in 1923, he accepted the post of acting Mayor of Manila. Artiaga would later leave Manila, serving as Mayor of Zamboanga, Mayor of Davao, and Governor of Bukidnon Province.
Throughout his career, Artiaga maintained his association with the School of Engineering of The University of Michigan. As one of the first Philippine students to attend the University, Artiaga gained the attention of Dean Mortimer E. Cooley. The two became close friends and began a correspondence when Artiaga returned to the Philippines. In their letters these two engineers discussed the direction of their careers and specific engineering projects on which they were engaged. Artiaga's correspondence with Cooley provides interesting comments on his engineering career in the Philippines.
A large part of Artiaga's papers concern his activities as Governor of Bukidnon Province. These materials, in both Spanish and English, include the minutes of the provincial board, official correspondence, miscellaneous technical reports, and some photographs. The remainder of his papers relate to The University of Michigan and his activities within The University of Michigan Alumni Club of the Philippines in the period of 1950-1957. In addition to his correspondence with Mortimer Cooley, there is a letter written in 1931 regarding the visit of Michigan Senator Arthur H. Vandenberg to the Philippines. There is also information about Frank Murphy, Governor General of the Philippines located in Artiaga's 1933 correspondence with Mortimer Cooley. Some of Artiaga's other correspondents are University of Michigan professors and administrators, including George G. Brown, Mortimer E. Cooley, Ivan C. Crawford, Joseph R. Hayden, James K. Pollock, Alexander G. Ruthven, Shirley W. Smith, and T. Hawley Tapping.
Subjects:
Artiaga, Santiago, 1878-1962.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Artiaga, Santiago, 1878-1962.
Contributors:
Brown, George Granger, 1896-; Crawford, Ivan Charles, 1886-1960.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.; Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Tapping, Theodore Hawley, 1889-1969.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Miscellaneous personal papers
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
  - Papers
    - 1927 (Box 1)
    - 1936-1939 (Box 1)
      (primarily October-December 1939)
    - 1940, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1941-1957, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Mortimer E. Cooley
    (primarily incoming letters from Cooley with occasional outgoing carbon copies by Artiaga)
    - 1914-1945, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Christmas cards from Mortimer E. Cooley (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Artiaga (Box 1)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Brown, George Granger, 1896-1957.
1951
Crawford, Ivan Charles, 1886-1960.
1950s
Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.
1939, 1945
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-
1952
Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-
1951, 1952
Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.
1951, 1952
Tapping, Theodore Hawley, 1889-1969.
1948-1955 (re U-M alumni affairs)